<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: recipe | Hello. Yes, this is blog.]]></title>
  <link href="https://blog.robertpataki.com//categories/recipe/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="https://blog.robertpataki.com/"/>
  <updated>2017-01-02T12:41:40+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://blog.robertpataki.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Robert Pataki]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Delicious oven baked vegan fasirt]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.robertpataki.com/2015/08/31/delicious-oven-baked-vegan-fasirt/"/>
    <updated>2015-08-31T12:58:01+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.robertpataki.com/2015/08/31/delicious-oven-baked-vegan-fasirt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-intro">Hungarian fasirt is traditionally made using minced beef or pork, and deep fried in a lot of vegetable oil - very tasty but not so healthy, nor it is vegan :) The recipe below is a vegan alternative to this delicious bite-sized phenomena.</p>


<p>As opposed to deep frying I prefer using less (or even no oil at all) and oven bake the fasirt patties instead, but feel free to experiment with the recipe and see which method you prefer more.</p>

<h2>Time required</h2>

<p><strong>Preparation:</strong>        40 minutes<br/>
<strong>Cooking:</strong>            25 minutes</p>

<h2>Ingredients (for 3)</h2>

<ul>
<li>&frac12; onion</li>
<li>150 grams of soya mince</li>
<li>Oat flakes</li>
<li>Olive oil</li>
<li>3 cloves of garlic</li>
<li>1 medium carrot</li>
<li>A small bunch of fresh parsley</li>
<li>Sea salt, ground black pepper, dried marjoram, red paprika, dried coriander</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/vegan-fasirt-1-preview.jpg" title="Ingredients are ready to be mixed and mashed to make vegan fasirt" ></p>

<h2>Preparation</h2>

<ul>
<li>Put the soya mince into a large bowl and cover it with water, let it soak it all up</li>
<li>Chop up the onion into very fine dices</li>
<li>Grate the carrot finely</li>
<li>Chop the parsley very finely</li>
<li>Add the seasoning to taste</li>
<li>Add a tiny bit of olive oil</li>
<li>Add a handful of oat flakes</li>
<li>Crush the garlic and add it to the bowl</li>
<li>Once the soya mince soaked up the water, add all the ingredients to the bowl and mix it well together</li>
</ul>


<h2>Shaping the patties</h2>

<p>To make the fasirt mixture nice and consistent, you will have to keep balancing the amount of olive oil and oat flakes you&rsquo;re adding to the mix (too much oil will make it too moist, too much oats will make it too dry and will make the patties fall apart). This is important, as you don&rsquo;t want your patties to fall apart.</p>

<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/vegan-fasirt-2-preview.jpg" title="All ingredients meshed together, ready to form the fasirt patties" ></p>

<p>Once your mixture is ready, you should be able to form little balls, which won&rsquo;t fall apart as you shape them. Place your patties on a tin foiled plate and put them in the fridge to chill for ~30 minutes.</p>

<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/vegan-fasirt-3-preview.jpg" title="Fasirt patties ready to be oven baked or fried in a pen" ></p>

<h2>Cooking</h2>

<ul>
<li>Take the patties out the fridge</li>
<li>Heat up the oven to ~220°C</li>
<li>Place the patties into an oven dish and leave them in the oven for about 25 minutes, or until they get golden brown.</li>
</ul>


<p>You can serve the patties with virtually any sides - rice, cooked or mashed potatoes, or some fresh bread :)</p>

<p>Enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's cook chunky veg soup]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.robertpataki.com/2015/03/29/chunky-veg-soup/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-29T21:38:45+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.robertpataki.com/2015/03/29/chunky-veg-soup</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-intro">What can you do when you have an awful cold? Cooking your own veg soup comes to the rescue! It is not only making you feel better when eating it, but it is also fun and easy to make!</p>


<h2>Time required</h2>

<p><strong>Preparation:</strong>        10 minutes<br/>
<strong>Cooking:</strong>            20-30 minutes (depending on how crunchy you like your veg)</p>

<h2>Ingredients (for 2)</h2>

<ul>
<li>1 pepper</li>
<li>3 medium sized white mushrooms (or any other mushrooms)</li>
<li>3 XL cloves of garlic</li>
<li>1 onion</li>
<li>4-5 florets of broccoli</li>
<li>1 large carrot</li>
<li>1 medium sized parsnip</li>
<li>Sea salt, ground black pepper</li>
<li>1 veg stock cube</li>
<li>Chillies (fresh or dried)</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/chunky-veg-soup-2-preview.jpg" title="All that lovely veg chopped up and ready to be cooked" ></p>

<h2>Preparation and cooking</h2>

<ul>
<li>Wash and peel your veg</li>
<li>Chop up the carrots, mushrooms, parsnips and broccoli into nice (but not too small) chunks</li>
<li>Dice up half of the onion and cook it on olive oil until it gets nice and see through. Add some salt to the oil, so that the onion won’t burn. Leave the other half of the onion intact</li>
<li>Once the onion is ready put your veg into the pan and add some water to the mix, turn up the heat to a bit above medium and cover it up with a lid.</li>
<li>Once it is all boiling, add some more salt, ground black pepper and the veg stock cube</li>
<li>Add chillies</li>
<li>Cook it until the carrots are medium soft (still nicely crunchy but not too hard)</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/chunky-veg-soup-1-preview.jpg" title="Serving the veg soup with some chilly" ></p>

<p>Enjoy and get well soon!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's cook Chilli con carne]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.robertpataki.com/2014/11/09/chilli-con-carne/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-09T12:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.robertpataki.com/2014/11/09/chilli-con-carne</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-intro">I remember my mum&#8217;s finest chilli con carne recipe from when I was little. It had loads of minced beef in it, and we used to have it with fresh bread and sour cream - we&#8217;re Hungarian after all. This is the kind of meal you always have seconds of.</p>


<p>This is one of those recipes I learnt from my mum but through the years I have sligthly altered it - especially since I have been a vegan. Apparently this is one of my best recipes, so here it is: I&rsquo;ll reveal my secret and show you how to cook a fine vegan chilli con carne!</p>

<h2>Time required</h2>

<p><strong>Preparation:</strong>        10 minutes<br/>
<strong>Cooking:</strong>            30 minutes</p>

<h2>Ingredients (for 2)</h2>

<ul>
<li>&frac12; tbsp coconut oil</li>
<li>1 medium size onion</li>
<li>2 large gloves of garlic</li>
<li>90 grams of soya mince</li>
<li>&frac14; tbsp paprika powder</li>
<li>1 (~400g) tin of chopped tomatoes</li>
<li>1 (~400g)tin of canellini beans</li>
<li>1 (~400g) tin or red kidney beans</li>
<li>1 (~400g) tin of black beans</li>
<li>1 (~400g) tin of white butter beans</li>
<li>1 (~400g) tin of sweetcorn</li>
<li>salt, black pepper to taste</li>
<li>1 or 2 dry morich chilli (you can use any sort of chilli really)</li>
</ul>


<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/chilli-con-carne-3-preview.jpg" title="A few tins of beans" ></p>

<h2>Preparation</h2>

<ol>
<li>Pour 300 ml of water into a bowl and let the soya soak in until it absorbs most of the water</li>
<li>Chop up the onion into small dices, chop up and crush the garlic</li>
<li>Slice up the chilli</li>
</ol>


<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/chilli-con-carne-1-preview.jpg" title="The colourful mixture of the beans and sweetcorn in the saucepan" ></p>

<h2>Cooking</h2>

<ol>
<li>Once the mince is ready place a large saucepan on medium heat (4/10 on electric cooker), add the coconut oil, the onion and the garlic. Add some salt, so that the onion won&rsquo;t burn and stir frequently until the onions are slightly translucent and soft.</li>
<li>Once the onion is ready add the soya mince and a bit of water and turn up the heat a bit (7/10 on electric cooker) to bring it to boil.</li>
<li>When the contents are boiling add the beans, the sweetcorn, the seasoning, and the chillies. Give it a good stir and cover it up with a lid.</li>
<li>Cook for about 30 minutes, stir occasionally to make sure it&rsquo;s not sticking and it is cooking nicely.</li>
<li>Once done with the cooking, remove it from the hot hob, uncover it, and let it cool for a while.</li>
</ol>


<h2>Serving</h2>

<p>I usually serve my chilli with fresh sour dough bread and a bit of Sojade.</p>

<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/chilli-con-carne-2-preview.jpg" title="Just a serving suggestion" ></p>

<p>Provecho / enjoy!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Let's cook stuffed portobello mushrooms]]></title>
    <link href="https://blog.robertpataki.com/2014/09/19/stuffed-portobello-mushrooms/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-19T18:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>https://blog.robertpataki.com/2014/09/19/stuffed-portobello-mushrooms</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p class="post-intro">The other day I was searching for some cooking inspiration, and I stumbled upon a very nice <a class="link" href="http://blog.fatfreevegan.com/2008/08/roasted-eggplant-almond-dip.html" target="_blank">vegan recipe</a>. After making that delicious dip myself I started thinking how I could turn it into a mushroom stuffing, so I started experimenting, and I replaced the aubergines with courgettes, and I did some minor alterations to the original recipe. I was quite happy with the result, so I thought I&#8217;d share this tasty vegan creation with others.</p>


<h2>Ingredients (for 4)</h2>

<ul>
<li> 4 portobello mushrooms</li>
<li> 1 cup of brown rice</li>
<li> &frac12; table spoon of coconut fat (or olive oil)</li>
</ul>


<h2>Ingredients for the sauce</h2>

<ul>
<li> 2 medium sized courgettes</li>
<li> 4 gloves of garlic</li>
<li> 1 medium sized onion</li>
<li> 1 small slice of ginger</li>
<li> &frac14; cup of mustard seeds</li>
<li> &frac14; cup of almonds</li>
<li> &frac34; cube of vegetable stock</li>
<li> 1 red pepper</li>
<li> 1 table spoon of co-yo or soya yoghurt</li>
<li> salt, cayenne pepper, black pepper to taste</li>
</ul>


<h2>Preparation and cooking</h2>

<ol>
<li><p>Put the almond and the mustard seeds in a medium sized cooking pan and toast them slightly until the mustard seeds start to pop. Once they are done put them in the blender bowl.</p></li>
<li><p>On a low-ish heat cook the diced up onions and garlic (diced and crushed as well), and once the onion is becoming see-through, add &frac14; cup of water and the diced up corgettes and the pepper. Cook it for about 10 minutes on low heat, then add the vegetable stock, pepper and salt to taste.</p></li>
<li><p>Once the corgettes are cooked, take them off the heat and put them in the blender bowl. Add the co-yo (or soya yoghurt) and the ginger and blend it until it is nice and smooth. If it is too watery add some more almonds. If it&rsquo;s too solid, add some more co-yo.</p></li>
<li><p>Scoop the sauce onto each mushroom carefully, and place the mushrooms in a medium sized cooking dish (put some coconut fat at the bottom, so that the mushrooms won&rsquo;t stick). Once all mushrooms are comfortably covered with the sauce, place a few slices of fresh garlic on top of them. Place the dish in a preheated oven (425F or 230C) and cook for 30 minutes. Every 10 minutes check on the oven and move the mushrooms a bit around to make sure they don&rsquo;t stick to the bottom.</p></li>
<li><p>Place the rice in a medium sized pan on medium heat. Once the rice starts sizzling, pour water on it and bring to boil. Once boiling, add some salt, stir and cover the pan, and bring the heat down to minimum. After all the water is gone, bring off the heat and uncover.</p></li>
</ol>


<h2>Serving</h2>

<p>You can serve the meal with some fresh slices of cucumbers, parsley and tomatoes.</p>

<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/stuffed-portobello-mushrooms-2-preview.jpg" title="Serving the stuffed mushrooms on a plate with brown rice and tomatoes" ></p>

<h2>Using the leftover dip</h2>

<p>The leftover dip is perfect to be used as spread on some fresh bread! Put it on a slice of fresh sourdough bread with a pinch of salt and some chillies and enjoy it for breakfast the next morning :)</p>

<p><img class="post-photo" src="/images/posts/stuffed-portobello-mushrooms-1-preview.jpg" title="Serving the leftover stfuffing as spread on some sourdough bread with green peppers and red chilli" ></p>

<p>I hope you will enjoy this recipe, and once you tried it please let me know in the comments how it worked out for you - or if there is anything you&rsquo;d change to make it better!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
